Finding Aid for National Housewives' League of America Records ca. 1918-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
National Housewives' League of America Records circa 1918-1996 1941-1987
National Housewives' League of America.
Organization established in 1933 to encourage African American housewives to patronize African American-owned businesses. The national organization was comprised of local groups, the most important of these being the Housewives' League of Detroit, which was founded in 1930 under the leadership of Fannie B. Peck. The Detroit League worked in conjunction with the Booker T. Washington Trade Association whose organization was headed by the Rev. William H. Peck, and the National Negro Business League. The record group includes minutes, correspondence, publications, and activity files of both the national organization and the Detroit league. The series in the record group are History and Organization; Core Records; Correspondence; Programs and Events; Media Coverage; Publications; Chapters; Related Organizations; and Other Materials. The largest portion of the Chapters series consists of records of the Detroit league and include history, publications, and other organizational materials.
0080 Bd 2
2.3 linear feet
1 oversize items
471 MB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 8892 ) was deposited with the library by Lydia Hibbert for the organization in 1999 and 2000.
The record group is open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
The National Housewives' League of America, Inc. began as one of several organizations founded in the early part of the twentieth century to advance the economic status of African Americans. Its mission was to encourage African American housewives to patronize African American-owned businesses through "directed spending." The Rev. William H. Peck and his wife Fannie B. Peck, after hearing Alben L. Holsey of the National Negro Business League and Tuskegee Institute speak about the successes of the Colored Merchants Association and the New York Housewives' Association, were inspired to create similar organizations in Detroit. Rev. Peck organized the Booker T. Washington Trade Association in April 1930. Mrs. Peck, believing that the support of those women who controlled most household budgets -- housewives -- was essential to any business success, founded the Housewives' League of Detroit on June 10, 1930, with 50 members. In the next couple of years, Mrs. Peck went on to organize leagues in Cleveland, Cincinnati, and Toledo, Ohio; Indianapolis, Ind.; Pittsburgh, Pa.; Kansas City, Mo.; and Jacksonville, Fla. By 1932, Alben Holsey, impressed with the response of the women in the leagues, invited Mrs. Peck and the other league representatives to meet in New York City to form a national committee, which Mrs. Peck chaired. The following year, the national committee met in Durham, N.C., in concert with the National Negro Business League, and formally organized the National Housewives' League of America, Inc. Mrs. Peck was elected the first president of the organization.
Despite its early success, interest in the organization faltered somewhat between 1934 and 1940, with only the Detroit League maintaining a consistently high level of activity in the national organization. A turning point was reached in 1940 when the Detroit League entertained its parent organization, the National Negro Business League, as well as the national meeting of its own organizational body. Enthusiastic representatives from Memphis, Tenn.; Oklahoma City, Okla.; Cleveland, Ohio; New Orleans, La.; New York, N.Y.; and St. Louis, Mo., attended, and the organization was rejuvenated.
Over the next several decades, the League educated African American women about their purchasing power and encouraged them to support African American-owned businesses as well as those non-African American-owned businesses that employed African Americans. Activities supported by the local leagues included National Housewives' Day, to be held at a local church every year on the fourth Sunday in October; April National Trade Month; numerous contests, including the annual Scrapbook, Essay and Queen Contests; consumer education programs; awards for business and professional people; youth education groups, and Junior and Senior Units of the League. One of the most significant annual events was Fannie B. Peck Day, instituted at the national meeting of the organization in 1946. The third Sunday in May each year was designated as the day on which to celebrate Mrs. Peck's contributions to the organization, with 75 percent of the funds raised during that week to go to the National Housewives' League and the remainder to remain with local leagues for educational purposes.
In 1953, the National Housewives' League of America ceased to meet in conjunction with the National Negro Business League at its annual convention and became more independent, although the two organizations continued to have close and cooperative ties throughout the following decades. The League also maintained similarly close relations with the Booker T. Washington Trade Association and the Tuskegee Institute.
The Housewives' League of Detroit, as the original chapter of the organization and a source for many of the organization's national leaders, remained an extremely powerful political and social presence in Detroit throughout the twentieth century.
The National Housewives' League continuously attempted to adapt throughout the years to changes in society in order to bring its empowering message of "Buy, Boost, Build" to African-Americans, including changing the official name of the organization to National Housewives' League of America, Inc., For Economic Security in 1986. However, good intentions aside, an increasingly aging membership led to a final cessation of activity in 1996.
The National Housewives' League is notable for the creativity, strength, and determination exhibited by its leaders and members in striving to improve the economic status of African-Americans throughout the twentieth century through self-empowerment, entrepreneurship, and consumer support.
The National Housewives' League of America, Inc.'s records include general organizational records, correspondence, annual meeting reports, minutes, and programs, news clippings, publications, drafts of speeches, and event notices. There are also several photographs, an audio tape interview, and numerous types of ephemera, including the National Housewives League Annual Calendar. The financial records which exist are generally scanty and incomplete. There are also several miscellaneous African-American publications from the first half of the twentieth century located in the Related Organizations series under Miscellaneous Publications.
The National Housewives' League of America, Inc. Records are organized into nine series: History and Organization, Core Records, Correspondence, Programs and Events, Media Coverage, Publications, Chapters, Related Organizations, and Other Materials. The records of the Housewives' League of Detroit are a subseries of the Chapters series. Because the local Detroit chapter and the national body frequently shared and overlapped in leadership, it is often difficult to determine whether the hand-written minutes kept were for the national or local organization, so researchers should consider examining records on both levels for complete information.
Subjects:
Afro-American consumers--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-American consumers--United States.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Booker T. Washington Trade Association.; Detroit (Mich.)--Economic conditions.; Fuqua, Christina.; Hibbert, Lydia.; Housewives as consumers--United States.; Housewives as consumers--Michigan--Detroit.; Housewives' League of Detroit.; National Housewives' League of America.; National Negro Business League (U.S.); Peck, Fannie.; Peck, William H.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-Americans--Organizations--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Fuqua, Christina.; Housewives' League of Detroit.; National Housewives' League of America.; Peck, Fannie.
Contributors:
Housewives' League of Detroit.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- History and Organization
  The History and Organization series contains early histories of the organization, its incorporation papers, copies of the constitution and by-laws, papers concerning membership, information about officers (particularly second National Housewives' League of America president Christina Fuqua) and some organizational surveys.
  - History circa 1950-1960 (Box 1)
  - Incorporation Papers 1951 (Box 1)
  - Constitution and Bylaws circa 1940-1979 (Box 1)
  - Journal of Negro Business, 1948 (Box 1)
    (edition focusing on NHLA history)
  - Membership
    - General Information and Forms circa 1940-1976 (Box 1)
    - Officers
      - General Lists circa 1950-1990 (Box 1)
      - Christina Fuqua 1944-1987 (Box 1)
        (awards and newspaper clippings)
      - Helen Malloy Eulogy 1994 (Box 1)
  - Organizational Surveys 1966-1977 (Box 1)
- Core Records
  The Core Records consist of what few financial records exist, minutes of the annual meeting convention and the executive board, and a series of minute books, apparently in Christina Fuqua's hand, which do not clearly distinguish whether they are for the National organization, the Housewives League of Detroit, or both. The dates in these notebooks also skip around fairly randomly.
  - Financial Records 1948-1987 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - Annual Meeting
      - 1953-1958 (Box 1)
      - 1961-1964 (Box 1)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970-1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975-1979 (Box 1)
      - 1980-1984 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Executive Board
      - Annual Meeting 1977-1987 (Box 1)
      - Mid-Year and Miscellaneous Meetings 1950-1981 (Box 1)
    - Minute Books circa 1948-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes correspondence of the National Housewives' League from 1941 to 1996, with the bulk of that material between 1941 and 1987. Included are internal letters from the national organization to local chapters as well as correspondence with outside or related organizations.
  - 1941-1949, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1950-1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1963-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1981-1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Fragments and undated circa 1949-1960 (Box 1)
- Programs and Events
  The Programs and Events series contains copies of the Annual Meeting programs, papers concerning the various contests, details of national celebrations of Fannie B. Peck Day, miscellaneous national events, rough drafts of what appear to be speech notes, frequently concerning the economic and social status of African-Americans, and what little extent material remains concerning the organization's youth programs.
  - Annual Meeting Programs
    - 1933-1996, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Contests 1944-1987 (Box 2)
  - National Fannie B. Peck Day 1950-1978 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Events 1946-1982 (Box 2)
  - Speech Notes and Essays circa 1950-1970 (Box 2)
  - Youth Activities circa 1960s (Box 2)
- Media Coverage
  The Media Coverage series includes press releases from 1950 to 1974 and news clippings.
  - Press Releases 1950-1974 (Box 2)
  - News Clippings 1942-1983 (Box 2)
- Publications
  The Publications series contains informational pamphlets and bulletins published by the organization.
  - Informational and Miscellaneous circa 1940-1969 (Box 2)
  - Yellow Page Bulletins 1974 (Box 2)
- Chapters
  The Chapter series includes the major subseries of the Housewives' League of Detroit and miscellaneous materials related to other chapters.
  - Housewives' League of Detroit
    The records of the Housewives' League of Detroit consist of the following categories: History, Core Records, Correspondence, News Clippings, Programs and Events, and Publications. The researcher should consult the different histories of the Detroit chapter for background information. Correspondence and News Clippings contain materials specific to the Housewives' League of Detroit. Core Records include the Detroit League's incorporation papers, constitution and by-laws, membership lists, cards and forms, Michigan Annual Reports for 1977-1979, meeting minutes, and reports. The Programs and Events files concerns the league's anniversary celebrations, including its 50th anniversary in 1980, records of its Annual Council meetings, Detroit celebrations of Fannie B. Peck Day, copies of the Detroit League President's Annual Address from 1975 to 1978, and miscellaneous drafts of speech notes and essays, not clearly identified as to author, concerning local events. Within the Publications files are early information publications, Trade Week Guide for 1941-1947, Housewives' League Bulletin for 1948-1951, and the Detroit League's annual Spring Campaign Guide from 1964 to 1966.
    - History circa 1943-1963 (Box 2)
    - Core Records
      - Incorporation Papers 1947, 1976 (Box 2)
      - Constitution and Bylaws 1937-1979 (Box 2)
      - Deeds of Gift to Burton Historical Collection 1975-1989 (Box 2)
      - Membership Lists, Cards, and Forms circa 1940-1982 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Annual Report 1977-1979 (Box 2)
      - Minutes 1975-1980 (Box 2)
      - Reports 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1940s-1987 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - News Clippings 1931-1981 (Box 2)
    - Programs and Events
      - Anniversary Celebrations 1939-1984 (scattered) (Box 2)
      - 50th Anniversary 1980 (Box 2)
        (also folder in oversize Box 3)
      - Annual Council Meeting 1940-1980 (Box 2)
      - Fannie B. Peck Day 1968-1984 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Events 1941-1985 (Box 2)
      - President's Annual Address (Lydia Hibbert) 1975-1978 (Box 2)
      - Speech Notes and Essays circa 1944-1984 (Box 2)
    - Publications
      - Informational circa 1930s (Box 2)
      - Trade Week Guide, 1941-1947 (scanty) (Box 2)
      - Housewives' League Bulletin, 1948-1951 (Box 2)
      - Spring Campaign Guide, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Other Leagues
    - Histories circa 1951 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Papers 1946-1979 (Box 2)
- Related Organizations
  The Related Organizations series of the National Housewives' League of America records include subseries concerning the Booker T. Washington Trade Association, the National Negro Business League, and the Tuskegee Institute. Also included are miscellaneous African-American publications dating primarily from the first half of the 20th century, and news clippings related to the above organizations.
  - Booker T. Washington Trade Association 1932-1987 (Box 2)
  - National Negro Business League
    - Pamphlets, Forms and Miscellaneous 1941-1953 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1941-1950 (Box 2)
    - Meetings
      - 1940 (Box 2)
      - 1945-1987 (Box 2)
    - Journal of Negro Business, 1946-1948 (Box 2)
  - Tuskegee Institute
    - History 1950 (Box 2)
    - Service, 1940-1944 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Publications 1938-circa 1990 (Box 2)
  - News Clippings 1941-1974 (Box 2)
- Other Materials
  The Other Materials series includes ephemera such as buttons, a bumper sticker, award plaques and certificates, convention ribbons, an audio tape radio interview with Detroit League president Lydia Hibbert in 1976, photographs of individuals and groups, and calendars.
  - Buttons and Bumper sticker 1950, undated (Box 4)
  - Calendars 1949-1987 (Box 3)
  - Christina Fuqua Plaque (surrogate) 1980 (Box 4)
  - Convention Ribbons 1943-1984 (Box 4)
  - Lydia Hibbert Interview on WWJ Radio 1976, reel-to-reel audio tape (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Bicentennial Train? and Exhibit 1975 (Box 4)
    - Housewives' League of Detroit, 50th Anniversary Photographs 1980 (Box 4)
    - Portraits and Pairs circa 1950 (Box 4)
    - Group Shots circa 1918-1976 (Box 4)
      (include photographs of African American workers in the workroom and lunchroom of the Banner Garment Co. in Detroit, c. 1918)
    - Lydia Hibbert Interview on WWJ Radio, 1976 July 19, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
      - [Part 1], [0080-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Lydia Hibbert interviewed discussing support of black-owned businesses.)